<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for peace: or A sermon preached in St. Pauls Church in London. Iuly 9. 1637. By Henry Vertue, parson of the parish church of Alhollowes Honey-Lane in London</title>
            <author>Vertue, Henry, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850106</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15290</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15290)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1587:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for peace: or A sermon preached in St. Pauls Church in London. Iuly 9. 1637. By Henry Vertue, parson of the parish church of Alhollowes Honey-Lane in London</title>
                  <author>Vertue, Henry, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. F[lesher] for Iohn Clark neare S. Peters Church  in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on I1v, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Concord --  Religious aspects --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15290:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15290:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plea for Peace: <hi>OR</hi> A SERMON PREACHED in S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PAVLS Church in LONDON. <hi>Iuly</hi> 9. 1637.</p>
            <p>By HENRY VERTUE, Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Alhollowes Honey-Lane</hi> in LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for IOHN CLARK neare S. <hi>Peters Church</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:15290:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REcenſui concionem hanc, cui Titulus eſt <hi>[A Plea for Peace, &amp;c.]</hi> nec in ea quicquam reperio quo minus cum utilitate publica, imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>October 9. 1637.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sa: Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15290:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE THE LADY SARAH Counteſſe Dowager of Leiceſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon was preached in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church by the command of Authoritie. The choice of the ſubject was left to my owne diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: when ſeeing with griefe the breaches among us, and fearing to what they might come, I fell upon that, which now preſents it ſelfe to your Ladiſhips view, as ſtudious to caſt one bucket on theſe flames, to quench them, if it were poſsible: for who can ſit ſtill and keepe ſilence, when he ſees the proſperity of ſo famous and flouriſhing a Church as this, in which wee live, hazzarded by unbappy differences raiſed up by unquiet ſpirits?</p>
            <p>I was perſwaded by ſome, to make this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, thus preached, more publike, by committing
<pb facs="tcp:15290:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15290:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15290:4"/>it to the Preſſe, who were of opinion, that it might bee of uſe for that end, at which (God knowes) I aimed in the preaching of it, namely, the ſetling of the mindes of men, and the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them to a peaceable converſation: which if I may ſee in any meaſure effected, it will more joy mee, then the fooliſh ſpeeches of ſome lawleſſe tongues againſt me, for my peaceable endeavours, have been able to trouble me.</p>
            <p>And no ſooner had I reſolved upon the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this Sermon to publike view, but your Ladiſhip came to my mind, with ſome content to thinke, that now I might have an opportunity to bring my ſelfe againe to your Honors remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and to expreſſe my gratitude, for that favour and reſpect, which long fince both I and my parents received at your Ladiſhips hands. May it pleaſe you to accept of this poore pledge of my unfained and ſincere reſpect, to pardon my boldneſſe thus intruding on your Honour, and to beleeve, that, what I have or am, is at your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips ſervice, profeſsing my ſelfe to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all true obſervance, HENRY VERTUE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15290:4"/>
            <head>A Plea for Peace.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHES. 4.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Endeavouring to keepe the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath a rule,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. tom. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt, <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> which warrants my choice of this Text. <hi>Nobis Sacerdotibus id praecipuè curae ſit, ut ea vitia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecemus, quae in plurimos viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſerpere,</hi> that is, <hi>The ſtudy of us Prieſts,</hi> ſaith the Father, <hi>ought to bee eſpecially to bend our endeavours againſt thoſe ſinnes, which we ſee to bee moſt frequent and predominant.</hi> How diviſions abound among us, who ſees not? the more the pity: What ſonne of the Church may not readily acknowledge it now high time, to come with our buckets to quench theſe flames, if it be poſſible? Who ſhall or can judge it unſeaſonable, now to plead for peace, when we finde ſuch wide breaches among us? Nor can I make my Plea in better words, nor can I make choice of a better ground for it, then the paſſage now read: <hi>Endeavouring to keepe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt verſe of this Chapter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins the exhortatory part of his Epiſtle; and the firſt advice which he gives is generall, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes all the reſt, <hi>Walke worthy of the calling,</hi> &amp;c. but thence hee deſcends to the particulars inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15290:5"/>in that generall: And now the firſt thing, that he pleads for, is peace and unity, with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary prerequiſites of it, which being in the foregoing <hi>verſe,</hi> humility, meekneſſe, long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and mutuall forbearance; his maine Plea it ſelfe for unity wee have in the words now read, which hee contents not himſelfe barely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, but he ads to it a ſtrong argument for the backing of it, taken from the unparalleld neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſtians, in the <hi>verſes</hi> following. But the Apoſtles plea it ſelfe for peace and unity, is to be the ſubject of my diſcourſe at this time, and my errand, to you from heaven, to which I ſhall crave your attention for the preſent, and your obedience for the future, That yee endeavour to keepe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In this Plea, wee finde theſe particulars. 1. The ſubject of the plea, <hi>the unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> 2. The thing required, with reſpect to it, <hi>endeavouring to keepe it.</hi> 3. The courſe preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed for the preſervation of this unity, <hi>In the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt I ſeeme to wrong my Text, offering violence to it, by pulling it in pieces unneceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or be in danger to trouble you with coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies and tautologies, I ſhall chooſe rather to looke at it, and ſo to handle it, as one entire Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which is;</p>
            <p>That S. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſes his Chriſtian <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and in them, us, and all Chriſtians in the whole world, <hi>to endeavour to keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15290:5"/>
            <p> And in the handling of this Propoſition, I ſhall obſerve this order; 1. To explaine the termes, 2. to prove the point, 3. to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by way of Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The explication concernes the Parties to whom the advice is given, and the Advice it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the perſons, to whom the advice is given, they are, as I ſaid, the Chriſtian <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and all Chriſtians in the whole world, and in all ſucceeding times of the world. If that bee true which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies: <hi>The things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>which were written aforetime, were written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. de Spectat.</note> anſwerably to which, <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaies truely, <hi>Cum Iſraelitas Deus diſciplinae admonet vel objurgat, ad omnes habet,</hi> that is, <hi>When God doth admoniſh or chide the Iſraelites, he hath a reſpect to all: Cum Egypto vel Ethiopiae exiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um comminatur, in omnem Gentem peccatricem praejudicat.</hi> And <hi>when he threatens ruine to Egypt, or Ethiopia, hee gives ſentence aforehand againſt every ungodly Nation;</hi> then is it much more true, which the ſame Father affirmes of the Epiſtles of the holy Apoſtles: <hi>Ad omnes ſcripſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. contra Marcion l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dum ad quoſdam. The Apoſtle, writing to ſome, writ to all:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug tom. <hi>5.</hi> de Civit. Dei l. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> which alſo S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> affirmes of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle in particular: For, having by way of commendation ſaid, that hee furniſhed <hi>populos Dei,</hi> the people of God with more Epiſtles, than any of his fellow Apoſtles, he addes by way of explication: <hi>Non tantum illos, qui praeſentes ab eo videbantur, ſed &amp; illos, qui futuri praevidebantur,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15290:6"/>that is, <hi>not onely thoſe which hee ſaw for the preſent to bee the people of God, but thoſe alſo whom hee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw ſo to be in future times.</hi> So that here will be no ſcope, whereby to ſhift off this advice of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle; for it was not for them alone, to whom it was immediatly and at the firſt hand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, but for us alſo, yea for all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now for the Advice it ſelfe: and here, to make uſe of the aforeſaid diſtribution, wee have,</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The ſubject of the advice, <hi>the unity of the Spirit;</hi> concerning this, two things deſerve en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is unity in generall, and what it is in this place. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unity, notes the joyning together of more things though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, yea, though contrary, into one; as the joyning together of ſeverall bricks or hewen ſtones, or peeces of timber to make one houſe; the putting together of a body propagated from parents, and a ſoule immediatly created of God, to become one man; the making of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> one new man, who had beene before of ſuch different diſpoſitions and religions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween whom in that reſpect there had been ſuch enmity. In all theſe there is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unity. The unity here ſpoken of, is that of which wee reade, under the notion of <hi>gathering together into one all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.10. Epheſ. 2.14, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>both in heaven and in earth, and of making both Iewes and Gentiles one new man, one body, one Corporation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 19. Verſe 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>one family, one houſe, even one Temple,</hi> having one head, one Lord, one King, one foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15290:6"/>and corner-ſtone, even Chriſt, who is all in all. This unity then is no other, then <hi>unitas Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, the unity of the Church,</hi> as <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſaies well,<note place="margin">Zanch. in locum.</note> the conjunction and agreement of the body of Chriſt the Church, compoſed and made up of diuers people and men, coupled and combined under one head, Chriſt, be they <hi>Iews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles:</hi> And this is by S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. de conſid. ad Eugen l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> reckoning up ſundry ſorts of unity, called <hi>Vnitas conſentanea, cum per charitatem multorum hominum eſt cor unum, An unity of conſent, when, by charity paſsing mutually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween divers men, they are as if they had all, but one heart among them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But why is this unity of the Church called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the unity of the Spirit? Here In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters differ. Some by <hi>ſpirit,</hi> underſtand the ſoule of man, and ſo will have this unity of the Church, to be called the unity of the ſpirit, <hi>rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſubjecti,</hi> in relation to the ſubject of it, becauſe the ſoule, not the body is the ſubject of this unity; divers bodies, one ſoule and heart in all,<note place="margin">Acts 4.32.</note> as S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaks: the bodies of men diſperſed far and neare, their ſoules firmely knit together into one, ſo ſaies <hi>Eſtius, Vnitatem ſpiritus,</hi> the <hi>unity of the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſtius in locum.</note> that is, ſaies he, <hi>animorum inter vos conjunctionem, the conjunction of your minds among your ſelves.</hi> And <hi>Mariana</hi> thus layes downe the ſcope of the Apoſtle in this place,<note place="margin">Mariana in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Non vult Apoſtolus ſuos ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis &amp; opinionibus diſſentire, ſed ut idem ſapiant.</hi> The Apoſtle (ſaies he) <hi>would not have his Epheſians to diſſent in mind and opinion, but all to mind the ſame thing.</hi> To theſe learned <hi>Calvin</hi> aſſents:<note place="margin">Calv. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15290:7"/>ſpiritus quidam pro ſpiritali accipiunt, quam in nobis efficit Spiritus Dei, Some,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>by the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſpirit underſtand here ſpirits unity, which the Spirit of God works in us:</hi> hee addes, <hi>&amp; certè is ſolus eſt, qui nos reddit unanimes;</hi> and indeed its he alone that makes us to be of one mind; but yet he addes, <hi>Sed ego ſimpliciùs interpretor de animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum concordia:</hi> But I, ſaies he, doe rather under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it ſimply of the concord of our minds. And indeed hee knowes nothing, that knowes not the ſoule of man to be frequently in holy Writ, called the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.7. Num. 27.16.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit goes to God that gave it,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Wiſe man;</hi> ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> cals God, <hi>The God of the ſpirits of all fleſh;</hi> and the Apoſtle cals him, <hi>The Father of ſpirits.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12 9.</note> Yet others by the ſpirit under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the holy Ghoſt, the third Perſon of the ever and equally glorious Trinity, who is alſo in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not ſeldome, called <hi>the Spirit,</hi> without his attribute, <hi>holy,</hi> or any other, as by our Saviour particularly,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.8. Matt. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>So is every one,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>that is born of the Spirit;</hi> and ſo S. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Then was Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus led by the Spirit into the wilderneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> and thus they will have this unity of the Church cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the unity of the Spirit, ratione efficientis,</hi> with reſpect to the efficient of it: namely becauſe the holy Ghoſt is the Author of this unity,<note place="margin">Beza in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Vnitatem Spiritus,</hi> .i. <hi>cujus vinculum ſanctus Spiritus eſt; the unity of the ſpirit,</hi> that is, <hi>that unity, whereof the holy Ghoſt is the bond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. in locum.</note> ſaies <hi>Beza: Vnitatem ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quia per ſanctum Spiritum fit; the unity of the ſpirit, ſo called becauſe it is cauſed by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſaies <hi>Zanchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15290:7"/>
            <p> But theſe interpretations are not ſo croſſe, each to other, but that they may well enough conſiſt and ſtand together, as <hi>Muſculus</hi> ſaies well:<note place="margin">Muſc. in locum. Anſelm. in locum.</note> and ſo Saint <hi>Anſelme</hi> having firſt expounded it, <hi>Vnitatem ſpiritus,</hi> .i. <hi>unanimitatem voluntatis, ut ſit in vobis cor unum &amp; anima una; The unity of the ſpirit,</hi> that is, <hi>unanimity of will, ſo that there bee in you one heart and one ſoule,</hi> doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards adde the other expoſition; <hi>Soliciti ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare, &amp;c. id eſt, ſolicite ſervetis, quod à vobis non habetis, ſcilicet, unitatem, id eſt, quod vos eſtis facti unum, quia unitas illa eſt ſpiritus, id eſt, a Spiritu ſancto vobis conceſſa, &amp; ideo non eſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenda, ſed ſtudioſe retinenda. Endeavouring to keepe, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>carefully keepe that which you have not of your ſelves, namely, unity, whereby yee are all made one, becauſe this is the unity of the ſpirit, granted to you by the Holy Ghoſt, and therefore it is not to bee ſleighted, but ſtudiouſly to bee retained.</hi> And ſo this unity of the Church is in two reſpects, called the unity of the ſpirit:</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that it is not bodily, but a ſpirituall unity: there is not <hi>corporalis contactus,</hi> a bodily touching one of another, not the bodies of Chriſtians united into one, but their hearts and ſoules,<note place="margin">Acts 4.32.</note> as appeares from the fore-named paſſage of S. <hi>Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For that it is the holy Ghoſt that is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this unity: as the ſoule and body are united together by the ſpirits, the waſting of which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth death in the ſeparation of ſoule and body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder; ſo by the operation of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15290:8"/>working in us brotherly-love each to other, Chriſt hath coupled all his Elect, <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> into one body in Chriſt, and betweene themſelves: and this is that which the Apoſtle ſaies,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>We are all by one Spirit baptized into one body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The thing required with reſpect to this unity of the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to keepe it.</hi> And here are alſo two things. 1. The thing to bee ſtudied, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to keepe the unity of the ſpirit.</hi> 2. The ſtudy to bee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in and about it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> endeavouring it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The thing to bee ſtudied, <hi>ſervare unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſpiritus, to keepe the unity of the ſpirit:</hi> We are not put to make this unity, this is a worke beyond our ſpheare; it is a worke of Chriſt and his Spirit. It is God that makes us to bee of one minde: this unity is the conjunction of hearts and mindes, therefore it muſt needs bee acknowledged to bee the worke of that God, <hi>in whoſe hands alone are the hearts</hi> of all men,<note place="margin">Prov. 21.1.</note> even <hi>of Kings</hi> alſo, ſaies <hi>Solomon,</hi> and therefore wee finde this worke by the Apoſtle aſcribed to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Hee is our peace, who hath made both one,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle: of all men in the world it is true, <hi>potius collecti ſunt, quam colligunt,</hi> they are rather the gathered, then the gatherers, the ſubject, not the cauſes of this gathering into one. All that wee can doe, and all that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us, is, that this unity being made by Chriſt, and his Spirit, wee ſhould keepe it entire and inviolable. And here wee muſt know, that, as it concernes every particular man for himſelfe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15290:8"/>to keepe this unity, ſo (though this belongs eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to publike perſons) it concernes us to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vide for others, and to take care for them, that they be not rented and divided from the unity of the Church by ſchiſme and contention. Beſides alſo, as Chriſt hath cauſed an unity betweene God and us, who were before divided, and at oddes and enmity through ſinnes,<note place="margin">Eſay 59.2.</note> which <hi>ſeparate betweene God and us,</hi> ſo we muſt know, that it is a thing worthy to take up the ſtudy of a Chriſtian, to ſeeke to maintaine this unity, and to take heed that wee renew not that difference and enmity, which was formerly between God and us, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſing into ſin. But yet it is more properly the ſcope of the Apoſtle, to commend to our care the preſervation of that unity, which is between particular Chriſtians, the particular members of the Church, the myſticall body of Chriſt: and, about this, to exhort us, not ſo much to that care, which publike perſons ought to have of others, with reſpect to this unity, to preſerve them in it, or to reduce them to it, if by any meanes they bee drawn from it, (though this is not altogether to be excluded) as to that care, which every Chriſtian ought to have of himſelfe, to preſerve himſelfe in this unity, &amp; not to ſuffer himſelfe to be pulled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, much more not of himſelf to make a rent in it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſtudy, that is to bee employed in, and about this thing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>endeavouring to keepe it.</hi> This is well added, for there is no hope, that, while we live here, we ſhould be able perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly to keepe this unity, in reſpect of others, no,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15290:9"/>not in reſpect of our ſelves. I ſay not in reſpect of others: for there will bee unquiet men in the Church, men of factious diſpoſitions, men that will ſtudy parts-taking and faction, who will bee ready to ſtir up others to ſchiſme and contention, as earneſtly, as any the moſt peaceably diſpoſed can bee, to perſwade to peace and unity: men, that wil as buſily kindle and blow the fire of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, as any can be ready to bring their buckets for the quenching of it. Ambitious men, who hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting after honour and preferment in the Church, if they miſſe of it; envious men, who ſeeing others preferred, when themſelves are paſſed by, ſpare not to ſow the ſeeds of diſcord, and to ſet all in a combuſtion: men, that are proudly conceited of their owne devices, and contend tooth and naile for them, and if all things may not be in all points, to an haires breadth, as they would have them, they care not how they hazard the peace of the Church. Nor will there be wanting fit ſubjects, for ſuch blow-coales to worke upon; ſome men, that be ignorant, that know not how to judge of things, poore ſimple ſoules, though haply well meaning, who are eaſily ſeduced, to whom it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, according to that paſſage of <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>The ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beleeves every word,</hi> as not being able to judge of the devills ſtratagems: as it was in the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Abſalon, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went two hundred men out of Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.11.</note> 
               <hi>who were called and went in their ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, not knowing any thing:</hi> and ſome men, who, having in other reſpects particular diſcontents, are eaſily perſwaded to joine with, and to hearken
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15290:9"/>to thoſe that would ſeek to draw them into facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſchiſme from the unity of the Church. Theſe are as tinder ready to take fire from every the leaſt ſpark that falls on them, and as the chaffe eaſily blowne away by every the leaſt puffe of wind. Nor will it be halfe ſo eaſie for men peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably diſpoſed to perſwade them to remaine in the unity of the Church, as for turbulent ſpirits to prevaile with them to forſake it. Woe to us! how have we by lamentable experience found all this to bee too true among our ſelves? But I ſay further, that there will be no hope, while we live here below, to preſerve the unity of the Church entire, in reſpect of our ſelves, for there is not the beſt, nor the moſt holy man living, who hath not <hi>reliquias,</hi> the remainders of unruly paſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the vertues mentioned in the foregoing <hi>verſe,</hi> in regard of which even the beſt, while they beare about them theſe houſes of clay, will bee prone to ſchiſme and diſcord. How eminent both for place and abilities were S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas?</hi> and yet what a fearefull breach did there happen betweene them?<note place="margin">Acts 15.39.</note> 
               <hi>The contention,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Luke, was ſo ſharpe between them, that they departed aſunder, one from the other.</hi> We are yet under the hammer, and not yet fitly &amp; fully coupled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; perfect unity, never to be prevailed againſt, nor broken, is not to be expected in this life, but is reſerved for heaven, there to bee our portion, where our love ſhall be perfect, and our happineſs abſolute. Unity in this life cannot bee perfectly kept, but that, ſometimes for a ſeaſon, upon this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15290:10"/>or that occaſion, there may be, there will be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of judgement, and likely hereupon eſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of hearts and affections: all, that wee can doe, is to endeavour to keepe it, and this it is, which the Apoſtle doth require at our hands. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>endeavouring to keepe it,</hi> ſaies Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> And this word here uſed is emphaticall, it notes not a ſleight, overly, and perfunctory endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that would be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functoriè agere,</hi> ſo to doe a thing, as if wee cared not, whether we did it or no; but in that he uſes this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, its manifeſt, that hee requires of us an earneſt, diligent, and induſtrious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for the preſervation of this unity, and ſo the word is at all hands rendred, <hi>ſolicitè ſervantes, ſolicitouſly keeping,</hi> ſaies Saint <hi>Ambroſe: ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciti ſervare, ſolicitous to keepe it</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Hierome: ſatagitè ſervare, make it your buſineſſe to keepe it,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Syriack</hi> Tranſlator. So S. <hi>Anſelme, Vnitas illa ſpiritus non eſt negligenda ſed ſtudiosè retinenda, This unity of the Spirit is not ſleightly, but ſtudiouſly to be kept and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> So that it is, as if the Apoſtle had ſaid; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to preſerve this unity, tooth and naile; doe your utmoſt diligence, <hi>tanquam pro aris &amp; foris,</hi> as if it were for your life, and livelihood, and religion, and all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The courſe preſcribed for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this unity. The Apoſtle had ſaid, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keepe the unity of the Spirit, they might now ſay, But what courſe ſhall wee take, that we may preſerve it? The Apoſtle ſtaies not,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15290:10"/>till they ſhould ask him this queſtion, he prevents and anticipates them: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the bond of peace: he doth as it were with one breath tell them what they ſhould do, and how they may effect it. But, what is this, In the bond of peace? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is put for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; in, for, by: <hi>In the bond of peace,</hi> that is, by the bond of peace: By the bond of peace, that is, by peace, as by a bond: ſo <hi>Eſtius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſtius in locum.</note> 
               <hi>In vinculo pacis, i. e. pace tanquam vinculo quodam animos veſtros colligante. In the bond of peace, that is, peace, as a certaine bond, knitting your hearts together.</hi> So <hi>Saint Anſelme: In vinculo pacis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſel. in locum.</note> i. e. <hi>pax &amp; concordia exterior ſit quaſi nexus &amp; vinculum interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oris unitatis ſpiritus. In the bond of peace, that is, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and concord may ſerve as a tye and bond of the inward unity of the ſpirit.</hi> And a little after, having ſaid, <hi>Vnitas ſpiritus eſt ſtudiosè retinenda, The unity of the ſpirit is ſtudiouſly to be kept,</hi> he addes, <hi>Quam poteritis hoc modo ſervare, viz. in vinculo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, i. e. ut pax taliter inter vos habita, vinciat vos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimul &amp; conglutinet: which unity of the ſpirit ye may thus be able to keepe, namely, in the bond of peace, that is, if peace thus had among you, tye you in, and glew you together.</hi> And ſo our bleſſed Apoſtle contents not himſelf to teach them, and us in them, how to keep, and maintaine this unitie, but alſo, by way of illuſtration, he ſets forth the nature and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of peace by a ſimilitude fit for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, comparing peace to a bond, by which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things, being put together, are held together, and kept from falling aſunder. Take a fagot, and keep the band of it firme, and uncut, the fagot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15290:11"/>firme; cut or burne the band aſunder, and all the ſticks fall each from other: of ſuch nature and uſefulneſſe is peace; live we peaceably, and quietly together, and the unitie of the Church is preſerved and maintained; give we way to ſchiſme and contention, and the whole is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And this office of peace is excellently ſet forth by the Greeke word for peace, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which as by ſome it hath its notation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>dico, to ſpeake,</hi> becauſe in time of warre, <hi>ſilent leges, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes dirimuntur non verbis, ſed gladiis,</hi> the laws are ſilent, and differences are compoſed not with words, but with the ſword: but in time of peace controverſies are peaceably ended by laws and by pleading; ſo by others, it hath its riſe, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>necto</hi> to knit together, <hi>quia connectit diſsidentes in unum,</hi> becauſe it linkes together parties jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>So that the ſumme of all is this, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us by all poſſible meanes, and with all poſſible diligence to endeavor for peace one with another, by it as by a bond to keepe the unity of the Church, and not by ſchiſmes and contentions to violate it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Now to prove and demonſtrate the truth of the point, that it is our dutie, ſo to do.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Though it were in no other place of Scripture given in charge, yet this one teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony might well ſuffice. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giving this charge, not as an ordinarie man, guided by a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſpirit, but as the Pen-man of the holy Ghoſt, and immediately guided by that Spirit of truth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15290:11"/>and wiſedome, who is not lyable to errour and miſtakes in the advice which he gives: ſo that it is not ſo much Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as the great God by him, that gives this in charge; ſo that to any that ſhall in this point refuſe to yeeld obedience, we may well ſpeake in the words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>He that deſpiſeth, deſpiſeth not man, but God:</hi> as, if any man ſhall refuſe to obey a charge brought him from the King, and delivered in the Kings name by any meſſenger, though never ſo meane, he deſpiſeth not the meſſenger, but the King himſelfe, from whom, and in whoſe name it is delivered to him. But yet, to put all out of queſtion, behold how, as in other particulars, ſo in this, both teſtaments agree, breathing forth the ſame truth. In the old Teſtament heare we <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.14.</note> 
               <hi>Seeke peace and purſue it:</hi> ſeeke it, as the man his ſtray ſheepe,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.4.8.</note> as the woman her loſt groat, purſue it, as the Huntſman his game: heare the Prophet,<note place="margin">Zach 8.19.</note> love the truth and peace. In the new Teſtament, heare we firſt our bleſſed Saviour, the King, Counſellour, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of his Church, concerning whom the charge was given from heaven at his transfiguration,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>This is my beloved Sonne, heare him:</hi> and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom <hi>Moſes</hi> brings in God ſpeaking in ſo dreadfull a tone ſo long before,<note place="margin">Deut. 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever will not hearken to my words, which he ſhall ſpeake in my name, I will require it of him:</hi> and what is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, then the charge which he gave his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples? <hi>Have ſalt in your ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 9.50.</note> 
               <hi>and have peace one with another?</hi> Next heare we Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> with whom nothing is more familiar, nor he more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15290:12"/>in any thing, then in charges of this kinde. <hi>If it be poſsible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>and as much as lyes in you, have peace with all men.</hi> And, <hi>Let us follow after the things that make for peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 14 19.</note> Yea, where he ſaw this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell moſt neceſſarie, ſee how earneſt he is. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>brethren, in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that there be no diviſions among you, but be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement:</hi> ſee his earneſtneſſe in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering this charge, I beſeech you. I, that am the Apoſtle of the Gentiles beſeech you Gentiles. I might command you in a buſineſſe of this nature, but I forbeare to uſe all my power, I rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, and is there not <hi>locus precibus?</hi> are you inexorable? can you refuſe to hearken to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties of him, that hath done and ſuffered ſo much for your ſakes? I beſeech you, brethren; you are brethren, therefore let there be no diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I beſeech you in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. In the name of Chriſt, that is, ſay ſome, by the authoritie of Chriſt, as the officer in the Kings name. In this name I beſeech you, as if Chriſt by me did beſeech you, therefore let there be no diviſions. Or, in the name of Chriſt, that is, by the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, which you make, I beſeech you, to which all ſchiſmes and diviſions are moſt contrary, therefore let there be no divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Or, in the name of Chriſt, that is, ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the glory of Chriſt, to which all ſchiſmes in the Church are moſt prejudiciall: as you therefore tender the glory of Chriſt, then which nothing ſhould be more deare to us, let
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15290:12"/>there be no diviſions. And in the cloſe of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Epiſtle, this is his fare-well. <hi>Be of one minde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13 11</note> 
               <hi>live in peace.</hi> No leſſe earneſt is he in this kinde with his Philippians.<note place="margin">Phil. 2.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfill you my joy, that ye be like-minded, having the ſame love, being of one minde, of one accord, let nothing be done through ſtrife or vain-glory.</hi> And taking knowledge of ſome breach betweene 2. Chriſtian women, ſee how he applyes himſelfe to them. <hi>I beſeech</hi> Euodias,<note place="margin">Phil 4 2.</note> 
               <hi>and beſeech</hi> Syntiche, <hi>that they be of the ſame minde in the Lord:</hi> The ſame charge he gives to his Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians. <hi>Let the peace of God rule in your hearts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3 15.</note> This is ſpoken of peace betweene the members of the Church, called the peace of God, becauſe he commands it, and he works it. And finally to his Hebrews, <hi>Follow peace with all men, and holineſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 12.14.</note> And as he ſo frequently gives this in charge, ſo doth he no leſſe make it his humble ſuit to God for the Romanes.<note place="margin">Rom 15.5.</note> Now the God of patience and conſolation grant you to be like-minded one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another according to Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome may ſay, why all this? what makes the Apoſtle ſo earneſt? why ſhould we be ſo ſtudious of peace and unity, to preſerve and maintaine it? Liſten a while, and ye ſhall ſee good cauſe why.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe of the incomparable nearneſſe that is betweene Chriſtians, now being knit together by ſo many bands: heare the Apoſtle in the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes following: <hi>There is one body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4 4, 5, 6.</note> then we are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15290:13"/>one of another. <hi>One ſpirit:</hi> one holy Ghoſt quickning us all, as all the members of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body are enlivened by one ſoule: <hi>called to one hope of our calling:</hi> the ſame glorious inheritance, to the joynt hope of which we are called by the Goſpell; then we are all of us co-heires. <hi>One Lord,</hi> then we are all of us fellow-ſervants. <hi>One faith,</hi> by which we all live, one doctrine of faith, which we all profeſſe. <hi>One baptiſme,</hi> by which we are all of us initiated into the Church, and one Lords Supper, as the common Sacrament of our ſpirituall nouriſhment: and ſo in generall we all of us participate in the ſame Sacraments: finally, <hi>One God,</hi> whom we all worſhip, who is alſo a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Father</hi> to us <hi>all,</hi> then we are brethren. <hi>A three-fold cord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 4.12.</note> ſaith <hi>Solomon, is not eaſily broken.</hi> Behold, here is a ſeven-fold cord, and ſhall not this hold us together?<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>8.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sub uno capite regimur, uno ſpiritu vivimus, unam patriam deſideramus omnes: We are governed under one head, we live by one ſpirit, we all deſire one countrey,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the three former of theſe bonds. <hi>Vnius corporis membra ſumus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>unum habemus caput, unâ perfundimur gratiâ, uno pane vivimus, unâ incedimus viâ, câdem habitamus domo.</hi> We are all members of one body, we have one head, we are all waſhed with the ſame grace, we live by the ſame bread, we walk in the ſame way, we dwell in the ſame houſe, ſaith <hi>Paulinus</hi> to Saint <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Were it no more, then that we are brethren, nothing were more unkindly then contention: who knows not, how unnaturall it were for brethren to fall out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15290:13"/>one with another? It was <hi>Abrahams</hi> argument to his kinſman <hi>Lot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>Let there be no ſtrife betweene mee and thee, for we are brethren.</hi> Brethren, we are of the neareſt kinde, having both the ſame Father, God, who is the <hi>father of all,</hi> and one mother,<note place="margin">Eph. 4 6. Gal 4 26.</note> the Church, <hi>who is the mother of us all:</hi> therefore no counſell can better fit us, then that,<note place="margin">Gen 45 24</note> which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> gave his brethren, <hi>See yee fall not out by the way.</hi> By this argument from the nee reneſſe of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>8.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> argues againſt the ſchiſme of the <hi>Donatiſts: fratres ſumus, unum Deum invocamus, in unum Chriſtum credimus, unum Euangelium au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus, unum pſalmum cantamus, unum Amen reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus, unum Alleluja reſonamus, unum Paſcha cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bramus, quid tu foris es? ego intus ſum. We are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, we call upon one God, we beleeve in one Chriſt, we heare one Goſpell, we ſing the ſame Pſalmes, wee anſwer the ſame Amen, we eccho forth the ſame Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah, we celebrate the ſame Eaſter, why art thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and I within?</hi> And elſewhere,<note place="margin">Aug. tom <hi>7.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te <hi>1</hi> de Emeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ad Eccleſ. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaricuſ. plebem.</note> 
               <hi>Qui adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus unum Patrem, cur non agnoſcimus unam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem? Since we worſhip one Father, why doe wee not acknowledge one mother?</hi> And by the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſets upon the Arrians <hi>Si mecum es in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug tom. <hi>6.</hi> de <hi>5.</hi> haereſ. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quare litigamus? una eſt nobis haereditas, poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deam us ſimul; fratres ſumus, ſimul ad cuſtodiam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditatis noſtrae vigilemus. If thou art with me in all things, why ſtrive we? we have one inheritance let us poſſeſſe it together; we are brethren, let us watch toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the keeping of our inheritance.</hi> In a word therefore, ſeeing Chriſtians are ſo nearely linked together, it ſtands us in hand to <hi>endeavour to keepe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15290:14"/>the unity of the Church in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe the divell is a great enemy to our peace, he knowes, its beſt fiſhing in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Its his maxime, <hi>Divide &amp; impera,</hi> ſet them together by the eares, and ſo prevaile againſt them, and therefore he doth all he can to divide us, and to ſow the ſeeds of diſcord among us, and it is his great content when he can effect it.<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>10.</hi> Serm. à Lovan. edit. Ser. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Satanae triumphus eſt Chriſtianorum diſſentio: the diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtians is the divels triumph,</hi> ſaies Saint <hi>Auſtin.</hi> And he wants not his inſtruments to fit his turne, ill-minded men, who are ready to blow the coales, to worke in us ill thoughts each of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo to occaſion private and perſonall brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yea to inject into us harſh and uncharitable thoughts againſt the Church, and the publike go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, ſo to make way for open and publike diſcord, to make us fall out with our Mother the Church,<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>38.</hi> ad Latum.</note> which is, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes well, <hi>Mater eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am patris tui, matriſque tuae quae nos de Chriſto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit, Martyrum ſanguine parturivit, in ſempiternam lucem peperit, fidei lacte nutrivit &amp; nutrit: the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo of thy father, and the mother of thy mother, which hath conceived us of Chriſt, hath travelled with us by the bloud of the Martyrs, hath brought us forth to an everlaſting light, and hath nouriſhed and doth nouriſh us with the milke of faith.</hi> And, if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould be wanting, the divell knowes how to make uſe of our ſelves againſt our ſelves, our own pride, ſelfe-love, and covetouſneſſe, which are the breeders and nurſes of ſchiſme and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: how then doth it ſtand us in hand, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15290:14"/>&amp;c. to make it our earneſt ſtudy, to endeavour it above, or at leaſt as much as any thing, to keep our unity and concord intire? for, who knowes not, that in places beſieged, the greateſt care is there to fortifie, where they finde the greateſt weakeneſſe, and the fierceſt aſſaults? It is the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets argument,
<q>
                  <l>Vt jugulent homines ſurgunt de nocte latrones,<note place="margin">Her. epiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vt teipſum ſerves, non expergiſceris? <hi>that is,</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Theeves riſe by night to kill men, wilt not thou awake to ſave thy ſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certes then the divell being ſo induſtrious to interrupt our peace, and being ſo ſufficiently fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht againſt us in this kinde, we had need, and it will well become us, to be as diligent to maintain our unity, that Satan have not cauſe given him by us to rejoyce, and triumph over us: according to that counſell, which Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> being now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, gave to a yong Biſhop.<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>75.</hi> ad Auxilium.</note> 
               <hi>Aufer litem &amp; revoca pacem, ne tibi pereat homo amicus, &amp; de vobis gaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at Diabolus inimicus. Take away ſtrife, and call back peace, leſt thou loſe a man thy friend, and the divell an enemy joy over you both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe of the excellency of peace: a thing it is of ſpeciall worth and high price; heare we that ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how he ſpeakes it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> 
               <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unity!</hi> Peace is comely, as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in good array, order and agreement. Its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull to the eye to ſee Chriſtians at unity, as it is acceptable to the eare to heare Bels or a Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inſtrument well tuned:<note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quae à Muſicis in cantu
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15290:15"/>dicitur eſſe harmonia, ea eſt concordia in civitate: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in the City is as harmony in muſicke,</hi> ſaid hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Scipio,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> alledges it. God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to be ſtiled,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11</note> 
               <hi>Deus pacis, the God of peace;</hi> Chriſt is <hi>princeps pacis, the Prince of peace,</hi> and <hi>King of Salem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 9 6. Hebr. 7 1. Eph. 6.15. Luke 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>that is, King of peace;</hi> the Goſpell is <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angelium pacis,</hi> the Goſpell of peace. Its a part of the Angels heavenly ditty, <hi>on earth peace.</hi> It is that good which our Saviour taught his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to wiſh to thoſe houſes into which they came,<note place="margin">Luke 10.5.</note> ſay, <hi>peace be unto this houſe.</hi> Its that good, which <hi>David</hi> taught his ſubjects to deſire for the Church,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.6.</note> 
               <hi>Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem.</hi> It is the beſt legacy which our Saviour could thinke of, to leave to his Diſciples, when he was to leave the world,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.26.</note> and to goe to his Father, <hi>My peace I leave with you.</hi> And who knowes not how its at all hands deſired?<note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sicut nemo eſt, qui gaudere nolit, ita nemo eſt, qui pacem habere nolit,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Auſtin: As there is no man that would not rejoyce, ſo there is no man that would not have peace.</hi> He goes on, <hi>pacis intentione &amp; bella geruntur, unde pacem conſtat eſſe belli optabilem finem: for peace ſake,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>wars are undertaken, peace being the deſired end of warre.</hi> And yet more, <hi>Et, qui per ſeditionem ſe ab alijs ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raverint, niſi qualemcunque pacis ſpeciem teneant, non efficiunt, quod intendunt: even ſeditious perſons, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating themſelves from others, faile in their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, except they maintaine ſome ſhew and ſemblance of peace among themſelves.</hi> One word more he addes there to the ſame purpoſe: <hi>Et latrones, ut tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius infeſti ſint paci caeterorum, pacem habere volunt ſociorum. Even theeves and robbers, that they may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15290:15"/>the more freely diſturbe the peace of others, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve agreement among themſelves.</hi> An argument that there is excellency and worth in peace, which thus drawes the hearts of good and bad af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeakes of it. <hi>Nil in rebus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renis gratius ſoleat audiri, nil deſiderabilius concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, nil melius inveniri. So excellent a thing is peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that we can heare of nothing, among the bleſsings of this life, more acceptable, wee can deſire nothing more deſireable, wee can finde nothing that is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> Nor is it a wonder, that he ſpeakes ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendently of the excellency of peace, it being as the ſame father ſayes, <hi>dilectionis mater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug tom. <hi>10.</hi> de Temp. ſerm. <hi>16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſanctitatis indicium, plebis ſanitas, gloriaſacerdotis, patriae laeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; terror hoſtium: the mother of love, a token of ſanctity, the health of the people, the Prieſts glory, the Countries joy, the enemies terror.</hi> Nor doth it weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argue the excellency of peace and unity, that the divell doth ſo ſtrongly oppoſe it. So foule a fiend would never fight againſt it ſo mightily, if he knew it not of great price, and ſpeciall excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. So deadly an enemy to mankinde would never ſo farre bend his forces againſt it, if he knew not the deſires of men juſtly carried to it. Whereas <hi>Campian</hi> and the reſt of the Ieſuites were, and are ready to lade <hi>Luther</hi> with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter invectives. <hi>Campian</hi> among the reſt calling him <hi>flagitioſum Apoſtatam, a wicked apoſtate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whitok. adverſ. ration. <hi>10.</hi> Camp.</note> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Whitaker</hi> returnes this anſwer, <hi>vium praeſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſſe oportet, quem homines improbi tam capitali odio inſectentur. Hee muſt needs be an eminent man whom ſuch wicked men proſecute with ſuch deadly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15290:16"/>No leſſe may we thus conclude concerning peace and unity of the Church: it muſt needs be of ſingular excellencie, that is ſo mightily op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned by ſo foule a fiend: and ſince by all theſe arguments peace appeareth to be ſo excellent, good cauſe there is that we ſtudy to maintaine it.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Becauſe of the uſefulneſſe of peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: it is many wayes profitable, and diviſions as hurtfull, and inconvenient: therefore peace and unitie is ſtudiouſly to be preſerved, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary as carefully to be avoided.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In regard of God; peace and unity among Chriſtians makes much for his honour; and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among us tend no leſſe to his diſhonour: <hi>Charitas laudat Deum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>149.</hi>
               </note> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin, diſcordia blaſphemat: Charity praiſes God, diſcord blaſphemes him.</hi> As in the family, the good agreement of children and ſervants is an honour to the maſter of the family; but if they ſhall be alway found quarrelling, and contending, it will be imputed to want of government: as we tender therefore the glory of God, which is the end of our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the attainment of which we ſhall provide for our happineſſe, it ſtands us in hand, according to the point in hand, to <hi>endeavour to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 In regard of the whole Church, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall members of it, the preſervation of peace and unity makes much for ſafety: there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes of continuing impregnable againſt all oppoſition of common foes, then is unity and concord among our ſelves, whereas on the other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15290:16"/>ſide breaches and diviſions tend directly to ruine: maintaining unity, we ſhall be ready to take part with, and to help one another: but falling out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, we ſtand aloofe off one from another, ſuffering our ſelves to be devoured by the common foe, while we look on: yea haply we ſhall be ready to act one againſt another,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.23.</note> and ſo to ſave the enemy a labour; as <hi>Moab</hi> againſt <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> againſt <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>Edom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both, ſheathing their ſwords each in other, ſo that <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> and his Iews need not to ſtrike a ſtroke. As <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.21.</note> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Iudah.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives a hint of this, <hi>If,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>ye bite and devour one another, take heed that ye be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed one of another.</hi> Who knows not, what a weakning it was to the kingdomes of Iſrael and Iudah, that they were ſo divided? How have the diviſions among the Chriſtians made way for, and given advantage not a little to the <hi>Turke</hi> for the making of an inroad upon Chriſtendome? <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> demonſtrates it to <hi>Achilles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hem Iliad. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that the diſcord betweene him and <hi>Agamemnon</hi> would in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood prove the ruine of the <hi>Greeks.</hi> It is a Dutch deviſe, and a good one to this purpoſe of two earthen pots ſwimming on the water with this motto, <hi>Frangimur ſi collidimur, We are broken all to pieces, if we claſh one againſt another.</hi> If two ſhips at Sea (being conſorts) ſhall be ſcattered by ſtorme each from other, how ſhall the one help the other? if yet they fall foule one upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how ſhall they not endanger one another?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15290:17"/>To this purpoſe is that of Saint <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. in Cant. Serm. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quicquid foris blandiri videtur, nulla eſt profectò conſolatio, ſi intus (quod abſit) ſeminarium diſcordiae germinave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Though the world ſeeme never ſo much to ſmile on us, we can have no comfort, if (which God forbid) we diſagree among our ſelves.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 12.25.</note> And this is avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our bleſſed Saviour. <hi>Every kingdome divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe is brought to deſolation, and every Citie or houſe divided againſt it ſelfe ſhall not ſtand.</hi> On this ground therefore it is,<note place="margin">Aug. de <hi>5.</hi> hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> that Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> gives that advice. <hi>Simul colligamus, ne dividendo perdamus,</hi> Let us gather together, leſt by diviſion we loſe all. But unity makes for ſafety, we ſhall be <hi>inſuperabiles,</hi> if we be <hi>inſeparabiles:</hi> Invincible, if inſeparable,<note place="margin">Bern. in Cant. Ser. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid à foris vos conturbare aut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſtare poſſet,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, ſi intus fraternâ pace gaudeatis? What from abroad can either trouble you or make you ſad, if ye enjoy brotherly peace among your ſelves? Pax vobis à vobis ſit, &amp; quicquid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecus minari videtur, non terret, quia non nocet. Be at peace among your ſelves, and howſoever the world may frowne upon you ye need not feare it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot hurt you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutar. de gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul.</note> And this did <hi>Scilurus</hi> that <hi>Scythian</hi> King in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> repreſent lively to his 80. ſonnes, when being now ready to dye, he commanded a bundle of arrows faſt bound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be brought unto him, which, ſo tyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he gave to his ſonnes one after another, that they ſhould breake them, if they could; and when they confeſſed, that they were not able to do it, he took them aſunder, and eaſily broke them one after another; hereby teaching them how
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15290:17"/>diſcord would undo them, but mutuall agreement would make them invincible. And thus heathen <hi>Scipio</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> alledges it out of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour) calls concord,<note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei, li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Optimum in omni Republica vinculum incolumitatis: the beſt bond of ſafety in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Common-wealth.</hi> If we then tender the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and proſperity of the Church, then which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be dearer to us, it nearly concernes us <hi>to endeavour to keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 In reſpect of particular Chriſtians, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church; our ſtudy to maintaine peace and unity, will be to them a matter of joy, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will more cheare them, then to ſee mutuall agreement among them, that call on the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and worſhip the ſame God, and profeſſe the ſame Faith, and participate in the ſame Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and are members of the ſame Church with themſelves, this being a ſure ground, whereupon they wax confident of the ſafety and impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate of the Church againſt all oppoſition of forreine foes, then which nothing can give them more content, as they deſire nothing more then it: and nothing will more ſpight common foes, while it puts them out of hope to thrive in their attempts againſt the Church. And on the other ſide, this as much as any thing ſads the hearts of Chriſtians, to ſee their fellow-Chriſtians, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> alway biting and ſnarling one at another: this giving them cauſe to feare, the ruine of the Church not to be farre off, the very thought of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15290:18"/>which ſtrikes them into aſtoniſhment: for thus we know, that any ingenuous man takes content in nothing more, then to ſee his common friends li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving friend-like together, and nothing goes more to the heart of him, then to finde them alwayes quarrelling and contending. Much more will the true members of the Church be ſo affected with the peace or diſcord of their fellow-members. <hi>Mutuis ſe vulneribus impetentes Chriſtiani,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. parab. de Chriſto &amp; Eccl. inter ſermon. de diverſis.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard, ſeque invicem hoſtiliter concidentes, hoſtibus à longè ſtantibus riſum &amp; inſultationem, Eccleſiae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò luctum &amp; incurabilem incuſſere dolorem. While Chriſtians like enemies wound and hack one another, they give occaſion to the enemies, looking on, of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and inſultation, but to the Church, of incurable griefe and ſorrow.</hi> How deeply was Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> affected with the breach which happened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> both aged men, learned men and formerly great friends? How did it make him breake forth into a paſſion of griefe?<note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>15.</hi> ad Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>Heu mihi</hi> (ſayes the Father) <hi>quod vos ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul alicubi invenire non poſſum. Woe is me that I cannot any where finde you together. Fortè, ut moveor, ut doleo, ut timeo, prociderem ad pedes veſtros, flerem, quantum valerem, rogarem quantum amarem, nunc unumquemque veſtrum pro ſeipſo, nunc utrumque pro alterutro, &amp; pro aliis, maximè pro infirmis, pro qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Chriſtus mortuus eſt. So I am moved at it, ſuch is the griefe and feare, which I have conceived for it, that I ſhould likely fall downe at your feet, I ſhould weepe till I could weepe no longer, as I love you, I ſhould entreat you, now both of you for each other, now each
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15290:18"/>of you for himſelfe, and for others, eſpecially for the weake, for whom Chriſt dyed.</hi> Would we then not grieve, but joy the hearts of our fellow-Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? would we not joy, but ſtrike ſadneſſe into the hearts of common foes? it ſtands us in hand, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the point in hand, to hearken to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calling upon us in his <hi>Philippians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any comfort of love, if any bowels and mercies, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill ye my joy, that ye be like-minded, having the ſame love, being of one minde, and of one accord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In reſpect of thoſe, who are yet ſtrangers from the Church; our ſtudy to maintaine peace and unity among our ſelves will be uſefull and available to draw them to a love and liking of the Religion profeſſed by us, and conſequently an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive to draw them into the Church, from which for the preſent they remaine ſtrangers: all men, that are in any degree ingenuous, liking that Religion beſt, the profeſſors whereof they finde to be moſt peaceable among themſelves and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous: for nothing is more available this way, then for thoſe that profeſſe Chriſts Religion,<note place="margin">Eph 4.1.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> injunction, <hi>to walke worthy of the calling, wherewith they are called,</hi> and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to it: for this is according to Saint <hi>Peter's</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, <hi>to have our converſation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>honeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note> beautifull: and who knows not, what a powerfull commander of affection Beauty is? Walke then anſwerably to our calling, and a troope will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, many ſhall, by meanes of it be added to the Church: would we ſo walke? endeavour then to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15290:19"/>maintaine unity: for this particular here in this verſe is joyned to the generall exhortation in the firſt verſe, as included in it, and a branch of it, as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, would ye walke worthy of your calling? endeavour then to keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace: And ſo we finde theſe elſe-where joyned together:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>Let your converſation be as it becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt;</hi> that is generall, and holds proportion with the exhortation in the firſt verſe of this Chapter: and anſwerably to the exhortation in this third verſe, he there addes, <hi>That ye ſtand faſt in one ſpirit, with one minde.</hi> Nor can this conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be juſtly queſtioned, for we are called to be children of God, who is the God of peace, to be members of Chriſt, who is the Prince of peace, and conſequently to be members one of another; &amp; in this reſpect it is, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are called to peace in one body:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.15.</note> And therfore how ſhall out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation better agree with our calling, then if we be thus ſtudious of peace &amp; unitie? nay, how ſhall not our carriage be quite contrary to our calling, if we be not ſo? For, for fellow-members not to be at peace, who knows not, how unnaturall it were? And in this reſpect by ſad experience we ſee, that nothing more holds off men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> embracing of our Religion, nothing doth more ſtumble and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize men, that are wavering, then the jarres and diſcords, which they ſee or heare to be among us. But there is nothing more deſireable, then to be inſtruments to winne men to God, nothing more to be avoided, then to be ſtumbling blocks in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15290:19"/>mens wayes to hinder them from comming to God: deſire we this conveniencie? would we avoid the contrary evill? it ſtands us then in hand, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>to walke worthy of our calling,</hi> and conſequently <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>to endeavour to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 In reſpect of our ſelves; this endeavour to keepe unitie and peace is uſefull in outward and inward reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Outwardly, it will be uſefull as conducing to externall proſperity, and length of dayes, by vertue of Gods promiſe: for this is one of Gods conditions, on which this is promiſed to us.<note place="margin">Pſal 34.12.14</note> 
               <hi>What man is he</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>that deſires life, and loves many dayes, that he may ſee good?</hi> the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in part is <hi>Seeke peace and purſue it:</hi> if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this conveniencie, look to fulfill this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, elſe we cannot on good grounds expect it. And indeed contentions may well and many wayes occaſion the loſſe of theſe conveniences, they being oft occaſions to ſhorten life, and alway to make it uncomfortable. Beſides, that God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doth puniſh breaches and diviſions in the Church among Chriſtians, by raiſing up ſome ſtorme againſt them, which may teach them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to agree, we being in this too like to ſheepe, which on a faire Sunne-ſhine day are ſcattered each from other upon the mountaines, but a ſtorm brings them together. So doth <hi>Euſebius</hi> relate,<note place="margin">Euſb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that the Church enjoying much peace &amp; freedom immediately before the perſecution raiſed againſt it by <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and making no better uſe of it,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15290:20"/>then to fall aſunder into diviſions, and factious contentions,<note place="margin">Lam. 2.1.</note> inſtantly God took a courſe, by way of puniſhment, <hi>to cover the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger, and to caſt downe from heaven to the earth the beauty of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89 42.</note> 
               <hi>and not to remember his foot-ſtool in the day of his anger, ſetting up the right hand of his Churches enemies, and making them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce</hi> If we then reſpect but externall convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it will ſtand us in hand to ſtudy peace &amp; unity.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Inwardly; we ſhall finde this ſtudy of peace in the Church, and among our ſelves to be uſefull three wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To be to our ſelves a comfortable ſigne of our condition: hence we may conclude, that Chriſt dwels in us <hi>Vbi pax ibi Chriſtus, quia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus pax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. tom. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>82.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Saint Ambroſe: where peace is, there Chriſt is, becauſe Chriſt is peace.</hi> Hence we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conclude, that the holy Ghoſt is given to us, as the earneſt of our inheritance, and conſequently, that we ſhall have the inheritance it ſelfe at laſt: for among the fruits of the ſpirit this is reckoned by the Apoſtle for one, <hi>peace,</hi> and the contrarie <hi>variance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22. Gal. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrife, ſeditions,</hi> among the works of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>9.</hi> in Jean. Euang tract. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> And to this purpoſe Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us, <hi>Oportere ſanctum Spiritum per columbam demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ut intelligat unuſquiſque, ſi habeat ſanctum Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſe habere debere cum fratribus veram pacem. That it was requiſite that the holy Ghoſt ſhould appeare in the likeneſſe of a Dove, that every man may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that if he have the holy Ghoſt, he ought to have true peace with the brethren.</hi> Yea hence we may conclude, that God is and will be with us, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15290:20"/>then what good can we want, enjoying him that is the fountaine of all good? And of this the holy Apoſtle gives us aſſurance, <hi>Be of one minde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi> But if we give our ſelves to live in contention and diſcord, woe be to us; we are ſtrangers from Chriſt, and have no intereſt in him: we are voyd of the Spirit of God. Saint <hi>Iude</hi> joynes theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. <hi>Theſe are they that ſeparate themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, not having the Spirit of God.</hi> Nay they are ſuch, as walk after the fleſh, and are carnall:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>while there be diviſions among you, are ye not earnall?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. And thus wallowing in the works of the fleſh, among which are reckoned contentions and diviſions, we muſt be content to take that which follows, that <hi>they which do ſuch things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5 21.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God.</hi> And not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing factiouſly diſpoſed and addicted to contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we can have no hope that the God of peace ſhould be with us, but alſo (ſince, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Onely by pride men make contentions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 13.10.</note> in reſpect of which every contentious perſon is alſo a proud perſon, and ſince, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.5.</note> God reſiſts the proud, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſets himſelfe in battell array againſt him) we may well conclude, that God will be ſurely againſt us, and then what ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can we expect?<note place="margin">Iam. 3.14. to the end.</note> And heare we what Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith. <hi>If ye have bitter envying, and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not, and lye not againſt the truth. This wiſedome deſcends not from above, but is carnall, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, divelliſh, for where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evill worke: but the wiſedome
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15290:21"/>that is from above is firſt pure, then peaceable, &amp;c. And the fruit of righteouſneſſe is ſowne in peace of them, that love peace.</hi> By which it is manifeſt, that our ſtudy to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace may certainly aſſure us, that the wiſedome which we have, is not carnall, ſenſuall, divelliſh, but from God, from above, and tends to God, and to heaven, and that the fruit of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, holineſſe here, and eternall life here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after is ſowne, that is, prepared for us, and ſhall be reaped and enjoyed by us, and what ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us if not this? whereas, contrariwiſe, he that lives in contention and ſtrife, though he may brag of his Chriſtianity, or otherwiſe boaſt of his wiſedome, yet in ſo doing he glories falſly, and lyes againſt the truth.<note place="margin">Ambr. tom. <hi>4.</hi> de Abr. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> That of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt true of this heavenly wiſedome, <hi>Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti pacis eſt ſtudium, imprudenti amicajurgia. The wiſe man ſtudies peace, the foole loves brangles.</hi> As we would then provide for our comfort, it mainly concernes us, according to this Apoſtolicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, to ſtudy unity and peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This ſtudy to maintain peace, will be availe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make us fit to ſerve God acceptably in the duties of his worſhip: now we ſhall be fit to pray with aſſurance to be heard and accepted; for this is required at our hands by the Apoſtle, <hi>to lift up pure hands without wrath;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tim. 2.8.</note> and to ſuch prayer aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is given of ſpeeding. <hi>If too of you,</hi> ſayes our Saviour,<note place="margin">Matth. 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall agree on earth as touching any thing which they ſhall aske, it ſhall be done for them of my Father which is in heaven.</hi> Agreeable to which is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15290:21"/>that of Saint <hi>Cyprian. Quic quid ſimul petitur à cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. epiſt. <hi>57.</hi> ad Cornel. in exilio.</note> 
               <hi>Deus pacis pacificis exhibet. Whatſoever is with an unanimous conſent prayed for by all the God of peace grants it to thoſe that are peaceably diſpoſed.</hi> Now we ſhall be fit to heare the word of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably and profitably; for this is alſo required of us in this reſpect, <hi>to lay aſide all ſuperfluity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo to receive with meekneſſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted word, that is able to ſave our ſoules.</hi> Now no leſſe ſhall we be fit to come with comfort to the holy Communion. <hi>If thou bringeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5 23.24</note> ſayes our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>thy gift to the Altar and there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, leave thy gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, and goe thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi> But, without this peaceable diſpoſition, nothing that thou canſt doe, can bee of any acceptance with God. An unblameable life will not ſtand thee in ſtead, while thou rendeſt thy ſelfe from the unity of the Church. <hi>Quiſquis ab Eccleſiâ Cathelicâ fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſeparatus,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> ad popil f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Quantumlibet laudabiliter vivere ſe exiſtimet, hoc ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcelere, quod ab unitate Chriſti disjunctus eſt, non habebit vitam, ſed ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dei manet ſuper eum. Whoſoever makes a rent from the Catholike Church, how commendably ſoever he may ſeeme to himſelfe to live, for this very wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe alone, that hee is disjoynted from the unity of Chriſt, he ſhall not have life, but the wrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides upon him.</hi> The uſe of the Sacraments will be of no advantage to thee, while thou ventureſt to breake the unity of the Church.<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Corporalia Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta,</hi> ſayes the ſame Father, <hi>Quae portant eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15290:22"/>ab Eccleſia ſegregati, formam poſſunt exhibere pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatis, virtus autem pietatis inviſibilis, ita in eis non poteſt eſſe, ſicut ſenſus non ſequitur hominis membrum à corpore amputatum. Thoſe bodily Sacraments which men, ſeparating from the Church, doe receive, may yeeld a forme of godlineſſe, but the inviſible power of godlineſſe can be no more in them, then ſenſe can be in the member that is cut off from the body.</hi> Nor in this caſe will thy Almeſ-deeds afford thee any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, be they never ſo abundant.<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>2.</hi> vel Fulgent. de fide ad Petr. Diacon.</note> 
               <hi>Si quis remanens alienus ab Eccleſiâ Catholicâ eleemoſynas largas dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, pro eo, quod in hac vita non tenet Eccleſiae unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, non habet vitam aeternam,</hi> ſayes the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or <hi>Fulgentius: If any man remaining a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the Catholike Church, ſhall giue large almes; even for this, that in this life he holds not the unity of the Church, he ſhall miſſe of life eternall.</hi> Nor canſt thou in this caſe have comfort in thy faſting, nor will it be of any acceptance with God, If the Iewes aske,<note place="margin">Eſa. 58.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Why have we faſted, and thou regardeſt it not?</hi> God returnes anſwer, <hi>Behold ye faſt for ſtrife and debate.</hi> Nay, ſhould it ſo happen, that a man violating the peace of the Church, ſhould ſuffer ought, neither in this could he have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>Si aliquis ex talibus</hi> (ſayes Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. epiſt. <hi>57.</hi> ad Cornelium in exilio.</note> that glorious Martyr, and famous Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſpeaking of the Novatians) <hi>fuerit apprehenſus, non eſt, quod ſibi tanquam de confeſsione nominis blandia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, cum conſtet, ſi occiſi ejuſmodi extra Eccleſiam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint, fidei coronam non eſſe, ſed poenam perfidiae: If any of them,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>ſhall be apprehended, they have no cauſe to flatter themſelves with the confeſsion of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15290:22"/>name of Chriſt, ſince it is manifeſt, that if ſuch ſhould fuffer death, out of the Church, it were not a Crown of faith, but a reward of diſloyalty.</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>Etſi oeciſus propter nomen fuerit extra Eccleſiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. epiſt. <hi>52.</hi> ad Antonian.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ab unitate &amp; charitate diviſus, coronari in morte non poterit: Though a man ſeparated from the unity of the Church, ſhould ſuffer death for the name of Chriſt, he could not be crowned in death.</hi> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> alſo tels <hi>Donatus</hi> as much, who was a Prieſt of the <hi>Donatiſts: foris ab Eccleſia conſtitutus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug epiſt. <hi>204.</hi> ad Donatum preibyt. Donat.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; à vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo charitatis ſeparatus, ſupplicio aeterno punireris, etſi pro Chriſti nomine vivus comburereris. Being out of the Church, and ſeparated from the bond of charity, thou ſhouldeſt be everlaſtingly puniſhed, though thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be burned alive for the name of Chriſt.</hi> Nor doe theſe holy Fathers ſay all this of their own heads, but as they have learned it from Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who plainly ſayes as much.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>Though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poore, and give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profits mee nothing.</hi> Nothing can be ſaid more plain for this purpoſe: for, if all this be unavaileable without charity, then ſo it is without a ſtudy of unity, charity, and the ſtudy of peace being undivided companions. As therefore we would not loſe our labour, nor ſtrip our ſelves of comfort in all that we doe or ſuffer, it ſtands us in hand according to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> injunctinn to ſtudy peace and unity.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To furniſh us with opportunities of doing and receiving good mutually by the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Communion of Saints: for God hath in ſingular wiſedome diſtributed his manifold
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15290:23"/>graces, not giving ſome all, and ſome none at all, but giving each man in the Church his proper ſhare, and dividing to each man his ſeverall gift, according to that ſtation in the Church, to which he hath deſigned him, ſo that as no man is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, ſo there is none, but may be in his way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall, there is none, but may ſtand in need of another; there is none, but may be uſefull to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>the head cannot ſay to the foot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.21. 2 Tim. 1.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>I have no need of thee.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtands in need of <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> his reliefe, and <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> needs Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> prayers. The ordinary Chriſtian ſtands in need of the Miniſters inſtruction, exhortation, and comfort, and there is not the moſt eminent Miniſter in the Church, who needs not the prayers of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Chriſtian: how earneſt therefore, and how frequent is Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in deſiring the prayers of Chriſtians for him?<note place="margin">Rom. 15.30.31.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you brethren, for the Lord Ieſus Chriſts ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, that ye ſtrive together with me in your prayers to God for me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, <hi>furthermore brethren pray for us.</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> writing to <hi>Darius</hi> a lay man. <hi>Ora pro me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>264.</hi> ad Darium.</note> 
               <hi>ne deficiam, ora, fili, ora; ſentio quid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, ſentio quid petam, non tibi videatur indignum, &amp; quaſi ultra merita tua, fraudabis me magno adjuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, ſi non feceris, &amp;c. Pray for me, that I faile not, pray, ſonne, pray: I know what I ſay, I know what I deſire: let it not ſeeme to thee an unfitting thing, and as it were beyond thy merits, thou ſhalt deprive me of a ſpeciall helpe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul de baptiſmo.</note> 
               <hi>if thou doe it not.</hi> So <hi>Tertullian. Ore, ut cum petitis, etiam Tertulliani peccatoris memineri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. I deſire that in your prayers, you would alſo remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15290:23"/>Tertullian <hi>a ſinner.</hi> And ſo Saint <hi>Bernard, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate me orationibus veſtris, ut ſemper poſsim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. in Cant. Ser. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; loqui quae oportet, &amp; opere implere, quae loquor. Helpe me with your prayers, that I may alway both ſpeake ſuch things as I ought, and practiſe what I ſpeake.</hi> In this regard who ſees not how uſefull it is to maintaine unity? For, ſo long as there is mutuall peace, there will be ſocietie, and ſo an opportunitie and readineſſe to do good by the employment of the abilities wherewith God hath in any kinde furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed us, and we ſhall be as ready to reape benefit by the abilities of others. But let peace be viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and way given to diſcord and jarring, and preſently there follows ſtrangeneſſe, we ſhall be ready to flye off one from another in time of need, and one to ſcorne to be beholding to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as therefore we deſire to reape the benefit of the communion of Saints, it ſtands us in hand to endeavour to keep peace and unity.</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the proofe of the point, wherein I have the more enlarged my ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the point is practicall: but the more I have ſpoken of this, the leſſe I ſhall need to dwell upon the application. To which I were now immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to come, but that there are two queſtions which need reſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. How farre and with whom muſt we minde and ſtudie peace? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Heare we the Apoſtle. <hi>If it be poſsible, and as much as lyes in you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>have peace with all men. With all men,</hi> then certainly with al them that live in the pales of the Church. <hi>If it be poſsible, and as much as lyes in you,</hi> ſaith the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15290:24"/>Apoſtle. There are caſes then, in which it is not for us to have peace with men: heare we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how the Scripture limits this ſtudy of peace. <hi>Love the truth and peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach 8.19. Heb 12 14.</note> ſaith the Prophet. <hi>Follow peace and holineſſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. No further therefore is peace to be maintained by us, then as may be without the prejudice of truth and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore 1. with Hereticks againſt the foundation we are to have no peace, no, not to bid them,<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 11.</note> God ſpeed; <hi>He that bids them God ſpeed,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Inſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliſ. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is partaker of his evill deeds.</hi> To this purpoſe <hi>Euſebius</hi> from <hi>Irenaeus</hi> relates, how Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the beloved Diſciple, going into the bath at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to waſh himſelfe, and finding <hi>Cerinthus</hi> the Hereticke in the bath, went away without waſhing, and ſaid. <hi>Fugiamus hinc, ne balneum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruat, in quo Cerinthus veritatis inimicus lavat. Let us flye hence, leſt the bath fall on our heads, in which</hi> Cerinthus <hi>the enemy of the truth waſhes himſelfe.</hi> And that <hi>Polycarpus</hi> meeting <hi>Marcion</hi> the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, and <hi>Marcion</hi> ſaying to him,<note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. <hi>t.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Agnoſcis nos? doſt thou not know us?</hi> refuſed to change any words with him, onely returning him that tart anſwer. <hi>Agnoſco te primogenitum Satanae, I know thee to be the eldeſt ſonne of the divell:</hi> In this caſe therefore it will be good for us to take up Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>6.</hi> contra Fauſtun Manich. l. <hi>29.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mancat potius nobis adverſus Manichaeos pro veritate certamen quàm cum illis in falſitate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia. Let us rather contend with the Manichees for the truth, then agree with them in falſhood.</hi> 2. With abhominable wicked perſons, blaſphemers, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, adulterers, and the like, in their ſinnes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15290:24"/>with ſuch maintaine no peace. So ſayes S. <hi>Auſtin. Pax cum bonis cuſtodienda eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug tom. <hi>10.</hi> de Temp. Ser. <hi>166.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non cum ſceleratis &amp; iniquis, qui pacem inter ſe habent, in peccatis ſuis. Pax cum bonis, bellum cum vitiis ſemper habendum eſt. Maintaine peace with thoſe that are good, not at any hand with wicked and unrighteous perſons, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining peace among themſelves in their ſinnes: we are alway to keepe peace with good men, but withall to bid battell againſt the vices of men.</hi> In theſe caſes, warre is better then peace, contention then concord; agreement in errour and ſinne is not peace, but conſpiracie: Chriſt had better have a troubled Church, then none at all: It is more for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, that there be in the Church truth and holineſſe with contention, then quietneſſe with hereſie and impiety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. But, doth this exhortation for the ſtudy of peace and unitie exclude all going to law for the deciding of controverſies happening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene men about <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> the proprietie of goods? <hi>Anſ.</hi> At no hand: God commands peace, he no where forbids us to make uſe of the Magiſtrate, and his laws for the preventing, or righting of wrongs. This may be, and peace not broken. We have, queſtionleſſe, heard of men, who having beene at law together, for the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of ſome difference happening betweene them, have yet travelled together from the place of their abode, up to this City, and have beene at bed and board together in a friendly manner. The Apoſtle therefore requiring the ſtudious preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of peace and unity, forbids not the other:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15290:25"/>onely this is required by vertue of this charge, that we go not to law for every trifle, but for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of importance, that we try all other fairer meanes firſt, that we make peace the end of our ſuits, that we be charitably affected each to other while the cauſe is depending: and finally, that we reſt quietly in the determination of the Iudge, howſoever the cauſe be ended, with, or againſt us, neither inſulting over the partie, whom we foile, nor envying or maligning in caſe we receive the foile.</p>
            <p>And now, theſe queſtions thus cleared.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Come we to the application: And here,</p>
            <p n="1">1 The world juſtly deſerves ſharpe reproofe for the ſcarſitie of peace, and the little care that men have to maintaine the unity of the Church. In which regard we may juſtly take up the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> in that cauſe.<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. orat. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pax ab omnibus laudatur, à paucis ſervatur. All men praiſe peace, few keepe it.</hi> The Papiſts in this caſe flie in our faces, as <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> for ſo they ordinarily brand us, objecting to us, that we have broken the peace, and made a rent in the Church; A breach there is, we confeſſe, but whether we or they be guiltie of it, let any indifferent man be judge. Onely for the manifeſtation of it, give me leave to repreſent to you a parable uſed by a reverend Prelate of this Church. A man invites his friend to a feaſt,<note place="margin">Joſ. Exon. co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumba Noe.</note> they eate and drinke together, and are merry; at laſt, the Maſter of the feaſt drinks to his gueſt, and gives him an apple, but ſuddenly a ſpider falls into the cup, and the apple is worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15290:25"/>whereupon the gueſt for the time abſtains; the Maſter of the feaſt urges his gueſt to eate of the apple, and to drinke of the wine: the gueſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes. It is not ſafe; ſee you not the ſpider in the cup? ſee you not the worme in the apple? let me firſt take out the ſpider, then I will drinke; let me cut out the worme, then I will eate, I like the wine well, and the apple, I like not theſe: hereupon the Maſter of the feaſt grows cholerick at his gueſt, as over-nice, he throws the diſhes and cups at his head, and at laſt ſhamefully thruſts him out of doores: ſay now whether of them hath broken the peace, and violated the laws of hoſpitalitie. It is juſt the caſe betweene the Papiſts and us. I hope then you will be able to give the ſentence, that it is not we, but they, that have broken the peace. But the particular application of the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as eaſie and obvious I leave to you: But for that, which they object to us, of the breaches and diviſions that are among our ſelves, in regard of which they are ready to conclude, that we are not a true Church; It were good they would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two things. 1. That we are not the firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene whom there have beene diviſions Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas;</hi> witneſſe Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> and <hi>Ruffinus;</hi> witneſſe the Eaſterne and Weſtern Church about the celebration of Eaſter: yet the two former couples were ſtill held godly men, eminent men, and the latter couple both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Churches of Chriſt. 2. That there are not wanting among themſelves great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and that about ſuch points as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15290:26"/>fundamentall points of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as about Purgatory, the bleſſed Virgin, the power of the Pope, and ſuch like: whereas the differences among us are onely in ſuperſtructures, in leſſe principall truths, whiles in the maine, and fundamentall points of our Religion we have (God be thanked) a firme concord, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the harmony of confeſſions. They ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are juſtly to go in the fore-front.</p>
            <p>Though yet it muſt with griefe be eonfeſſed, that many among our ſelves are fearfully guiltie of breaking the peace, and unitie of the Church; the more the pitie: ſome contending for and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout worldly things, maintaining tedious ſuits, ſometimes for trifles, not worthy to be named: ſome about Theologicall Articles, as <hi>Pareus</hi> calls them.<note place="margin">Par. Irenicon.</note> And the <hi>Diſciplinarians</hi> about innocent ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies enjoyned by the Church with reſpect to decencie and uniformity in the worſhip of God, concerning which God hath not in his Word given any expreſſe order, one way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leaving them to be ordered by the Church, according to thoſe generall rules layed downe in the Word about indifferent things. And yet about theſe things what fearfull breaches are among us? Some, not contenting themſelves, not to ſubmit to the authoritie of the Church, but endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet all in a combuſtion, not onely in private whiſpering againſt the Church, and the power of it, but alſo publiſhing and divulging ſcandalous libels, by which they ſtudy to make men our of love with the Government ſetled, pratling of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15290:26"/>and perſwading people that <hi>Popery</hi> muſt needs be creeping in, becauſe thoſe things, which tend to reverence and devotion, to order and decencie, are ſomewhat more ſtrictly urged now, then formerly they have beene: though it might eaſily be manifeſted, that theſe things were practiſed by the Chriſtian Church long before <hi>Popery</hi> was ſo much as thought on; as may eaſily appeare to any, that are in the leaſt manner skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the writings of the <hi>Ancients;</hi> and I doubt not, but the ignorance of <hi>Antiquity</hi> is one maine cauſe of this violent oppoſition. But let all that are guilty in this kinde, not being ſtudious of peace, but for theſe things breaking the unitie of the Church, let theſe, I ſay, know that they walk unworthy of their calling, that they have an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that they are carnall, and that their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is earthly, lenſuall, devilliſh: they ſay, they are Chriſtians, but it were to be wiſhed, they would walke as ſuch, leſt they be found to lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth:<note place="margin">Juſt. Mort. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. pro Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en. ad Anconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Pium.</note> Heare they what Saint <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſaid long ago, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>If any bee found not to live as Chriſt hath taught, it is a certaine argument that they are not Chriſtians, though with the tongue they confeſſe the doctrine of Chriſt: for not thoſe which onely profeſſe, but thoſe which ſecond their profeſsion with anſwerable works doth Chriſt aſſure of ſalvation.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. c. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> though more conciſely: <hi>Dicet aliquis, etiam de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15290:27"/>excedere quoſdam à regula diſciplinae: Some will ſay, that even ſome of our owne violate the rule of Chriſtianitie:</hi> but he anſwers, <hi>Deſinunt tunc Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani haberi penes nos. We then ceaſe to acknowledge them to be Chriſtians.</hi> Let not ſuch judge their ſinne to be ſmall,<note place="margin">Aug. tom <hi>7.</hi> parte <hi>1.</hi> contra Epiſt. Parmen. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> but know, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes, that <hi>Sacrilegium ſchiſmatis omnia ſcelera ſupergreditur, The ſacriledge of ſchiſme exceeds all ſinnes.</hi> And for proofe of this, let them take into conſideration, that other paſſage of the ſame Father.<note place="margin">Id. de Baptiſ. contra Donat. l. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sub veteri teſtamento idolum fabricatur &amp; adoratur,</hi> liber Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticus irâ Regis contemptoris incenditur, &amp; ſchiſma tentatur.<note place="margin">Exo. 32.3, 4, 5</note> 
               <hi>In the old Teſtament we reade of an Idoll made and worſhipped,</hi> even a golden calfe by the Iſraelites: <hi>a propheticall book burnt in a rage, by a contemptuous King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 36.23.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> book firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, then read by <hi>Baruch,</hi> laſtly cut in pieces, and burnt by <hi>Iehojakim:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and a ſchiſme attempted,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by <hi>Korah</hi> and his complices. <hi>Idololatria gladio punitur; exuſtio libri bellica caede &amp; captivitate, ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma hiatu terrae, authoribus vivis ſepultis, &amp; caeteris coeleſti igne conſumptis. The idolatry is puniſhed with the ſword, the burning of the book with warre-like ſlaughter and captivitie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.29.30.31.32.33</note> 
               <hi>but for the attempters of the ſchiſme a common viſitation will not ſerve, God will do a new thing, the earth opens her month, and the principals go downe quicke into the pit, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates are confumed with fire from heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 35.</note> 
               <hi>Quis jam dub tat,</hi> ſaith the Father, <hi>hoc eſſe ſceleratius, commiſſum, quod eſt gravius vindicatum? Who can now doubt, but that the ſinne is the greateſt, in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of which we finde the greateſt ſeveritie?</hi> Nor let ſuch men as theſe, flatter themſelves in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15290:27"/>their otherwiſe unblameable converſation, in their prayers, in their almes, nor in ought elſe, it being moſt true of all ſuch, that the ſame Father ſayes of the Donatiſts: <hi>omnia illa quae laudantur in Eccleſia, nihil illis proſunt, quia conſcindunt unitatem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan Euang. tract. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>All thoſe things,</hi> (namely virginity, continency, almes) <hi>profit them nothing, becauſe they violate the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church.</hi> Such men are worſe then thoſe rude Souldiers, who were the crucifiers of our Saviour: In which reſpect we may ſay of them, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> of the Donatiſts. <hi>Venit perſecutor &amp; non fregit crura Chriſti, venit Donatus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>34</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupit Eccleſiam Chriſti. Integrum corpus Chriſti eſt in cruce inter manus perſecutorum, &amp; inter manus Chriſtianorum non eſt integrum corpus Eccleſiae. The Souldiers comming broke not the legs of Chriſt, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus comming hath made a breach in the Church of Chriſt. The body of Chriſt remaines entire on the Croſſe in the hands of his enemies: and the body of the Church is not entire in the hands of Chriſtians:</hi> finally, let not ſuch expect peace and comfort in the concluſion, but except they repent of their attempts againſt the peace of the Church, let them be ſure of it, that, as they love wrath, they ſhall have wrath, and that, as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſpake to <hi>Achan,</hi> ſo it will be done to them, that as they have <hi>troubled Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſo God ſhall trouble them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 For a cloſe therefore, ſuffer a word of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: in the words of Saint <hi>Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that there be no diviſions among us, but be perfectly joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> At any hand, take we heed, that we be not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15290:28"/>leaders of others into ſchiſme from the unity of the Church: this would be in all reſpects as ill an office as we could poſſibly doe them, and of as dangerous conſequence to our ſelves. But, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not enough for us to abſtaine from evill, except we alſo ſet our ſelves to doe good, let us not content our ſelves not to draw others from the unity of the Church, doe we alſo our utmoſt diligence, to hold others in it, and to reduce them to it, in caſe we know any drawne from it: let the peace of the Church be deare to us: here let us uſe our beſt rhetoricke, and our moſt powerfull perſwaſions: Chriſt hath ſaid it: <hi>Bleſſed are the peace-makers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall be called the children of God:</hi> as we would ſhare in this bleſſedneſſe, let this be our ſtudy. Shall we be counted pick-thanks, and fiatterers, and time-ſervers, if we ſet our ſelves to this worke? Regard not ſuch uncharitable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſacrifice our credit and good name to the peace of the Church; be we regardleſſe of mens lawleſſe tongues in compariſon of a buſineſſe of ſo high a nature, and ſo ſpeciall advantage. May the deſire or attempting of this tend to our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſadvantage? let not this at any hand take us off from this endeavour. It was a good anſwer of Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> to the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>50.</hi> ad Beniſas. virum milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> and a holy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which he therein expreſſed. They obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>vos (Catholici) res noſtras concupiſcitis, &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertis: ye (Catholicks) covet and take away our goods:</hi> he anſwers, <hi>Vtinam Catholici fiant, &amp; non ſolum quae dicunt ſua, ſed &amp; noſtra cum charitate &amp; pace poſside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Would to God, they would become Gatholike Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15290:28"/>upon condition, that they poſſeſſed not onely their owne goods, but ours alſo with peace and charity.</hi> But we may be in danger to ſuffer hardſhip, if we thus ſet our ſelves to ſtudy the peace of the Church: Neither is this to be regarded.<note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dionyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> writing to <hi>Novatus,</hi> who, having diſturbed the peace of the Church, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that he was compelled by others ſo to doe, returns him this grave anſwer, <hi>Oportet nil non fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ne Eccleſiam Dei ſcinderes. Thou ſhouldeſt chuſe rather to ſuffer any thing, then ſo to diſturbe the Church.</hi> He addes, <hi>Nec eſt Martyrium hoc, Eccleſiae non ſcindendae gratiâ toleratum, minoris gloriae, quàm quod fertur propter Idololatriae recuſationem; Imò meo judicio majoris gloriae eſt, Illic enim pro unâ animâ martyrium toleratur, hic verò pro universâ Eccleſiâ. Neither is this martyrdome, ſuffered for not making a rent in the Church, leſſe glorious, then that, which is undergone for the refuſall of idolatry. Nay in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion it is more glorious: for in that a man ſuffers for the behoofe of one ſoule, in this for the behoofe of the whole Church.</hi> The ſame may no leſſe be ſaid of ſuffering ought for the ſtudy to retaine others in, or to reduce them to the unity of the Church. Therefore all excuſes laid aſide, let us all in our places bend our utmoſt endeavour this way. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, if any have been occaſions of breaches in the Church, let ſuch ſeeke to make amends by ſtudying by all meanes to reduce thoſe to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church whom they have been means to rend from it. <hi>Si perſuaſeris fratribus,</hi> ſayes <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> to <hi>Novatus</hi> in the aforeſaid Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Euſeb. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>vel coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geris
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15290:29"/>etiam, ut ad concordiam redeant, majus erit hoc factum tam eximium, quam delictum, quod praeceſsit, &amp; illud quidem, non imputabitur, hoc verò laudabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. If thou ſhalt perſwade the brethren, or if thou ſhalt alſo compell them to come againe to agreement, this good worke ſhall be greater then the offence, which went before, and that ſhall not be imputed, but this ſhall be prayſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sayes any, that this endeavour will be vaine, and the labour loſt? let no ſuch thoughts hinder us from this attempt: for, firſt, haply thou maiſt prevaile with them by the good hand of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy endeavour.<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</hi> ad Maximum Medicum.</note> 
               <hi>Abſit ut ipſe, nolent tecum recta ſentire,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Auſtin, Cum quo eos delectavit errare: abſit ut reſiſtant tibi vera dicenti, cui conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerant à veritate devianti. God forbid that they ſhould not joyne with thee in right thoughts, who delighted to erre with thee: God forbid that they ſhould reſiſt thee ſpeaking the truth, who conſented to thee deviating from the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 If thou canſt not prevaile with them, yet this will afford thee comfort, that thou haſt endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it. Thou mayeſt ſay with the Prophet, <hi>I have laboured in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 49.4.</note> 
               <hi>but my judgement is with the Lord, and my worke with my God.</hi> It is moſt true, that Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>7.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te <hi>1.</hi> contra Creſcon. Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si cui diligentia medicinae hujus impenſa non proſit, ſufficit ad rationem reddendam Deo, quod non ceſſavit impendi. If this my diligent endeavour beſtowed upon any, profit him not, yet it is ſufficient for my comfort in giving up my account to God, that I have not beene ſlacke, to uſe this diligence:</hi> he addes, <hi>ſicut enim ſuaſor peccati malignus, etſi non
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15290:29"/>perſuaſerit, meritò perſuaſor is panam incurrit, ita fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis juſtitiae praedicator, etſi ab hominibus reſpuatur, abſit, ut apud Deum ſui officij mercede defraudeiur: for, as he that ſhall wickedly aſſay to draw another to ſinne, though he prevaile not, doth yet deſervedly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre puniſhment, as if he had prevailed: So God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that the faithfull Preacher of righteouſneſſe, though he be rejected of men, ſhould miſſe of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with God:</hi> for ſo ſayes the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhall receive his owne reward according to his owne labour: ſecundum laborem, non ſecundum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum,</hi> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves:<note place="margin">Bern. de conſid. ad Eugen. l. <hi>4.</hi> c <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>according to his labour not according to his ſucceſſe in his labour.</hi> And, becauſe the ſucceſſe of our endeavours in all kindes depends upon the bleſſing of God, to our perſwaſions uſed towards them, adde alſo our prayers to God for them in the words of Saint <hi>Auſtin. Tranquillet Deus &amp; componat animos veſtros.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. to <hi>9.</hi> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tumultuantes.</note> 
               <hi>ut non in vobis praevaleat opu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diaboli ſed pax, Dei vincat in cordibus. God quiet and compoſe your minds, that the worke of the divell may not prevaile in you but the peace of God may rule &amp; beare ſway in your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at leaſt let us all looke to our ſelves that we for our owne parts endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. Suffer we not our ſelves to be rent from the unity of the Church; or, if we have been by any meanes drawn from it, let us at laſt readily returne to it: Conſider what hath been ſaid &amp; the Lord give us underſtanding in all things. Would we ſee good, and enjoy long dayes? would we be ſure that we have that wiſedome which is from above? be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15290:30"/>peaceable, wrangle not for trifles, contend not about uncertainties: Reſolve we with Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> that <hi>melius eſt dubitare de occultis, quàm litiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de incertis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>3.</hi> de Geneſ. ad lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram l. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Its better to be doubtfull concerning ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, then to be contentious about thoſe things which are uncertaine.</hi> We are brethren, let there be no ſtrife between us: we are travellers together to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the celeſtiall Canaan, ſee that we fall not out by the way. We have common foes, let us hold together that we may <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fight together for the faith of the Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes. Let the glory of God be precious to us, obſcure it not by our jarres; let the credit of religion be reſpected by us, blemiſh it not by our contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: tender the ſafety of the Church ſo farre, as not to hazard it by our broyles: In a word, <hi>live in peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>and the God of love and peace ſhall be with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this end I beſeech you, that my counſell may be acceptable to you in the following parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Abandon pride, and labour for humility: for, <hi>onely by pride,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov. 13.10.</hi> Bern. inter ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones de diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. ſer. <hi>1.</hi> de verb. Apoſtoli. <hi>Rom. 14.19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>men make contentions,</hi> ſayes <hi>Salomon. Impoſsibile eſt,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Bernard; Hic &amp; modò pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem inter nos ſervari, niſi &amp; qui in aliquo offendit fratrem, animoſam elationem, &amp; qui offenſus eſt, nihilominus caveat inexorabilem obſtinationem. It is impoſsible that here and now peace ſhould be preſerved among us, except both he, that in ſome thing offends his brother, beware of ſtomackfull haughtineſſe, and he that is offended, doe no leſſe take heed of inexorable obſtinacy.</hi> And therfore he preſcribes this rule for the maintenance of peace.<note place="margin">Jd. ibid. ſer. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si recordaris quòd frater
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15290:30"/>tuus habet aliquid adverſus te, ſis humilis ad peten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam veniam: ſi tu habeas adverſus illum, ſis facilis ad dandam, &amp; omnia erunt in pace. If thou remember that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, in humility crave pardon: If thou haſt ought againſt him, be ready to grant pardon, and all things ſhall be in peace.</hi> Pride diſables us for both theſe: a proud perſon ſcornes to ſtoop to acknowledge a fault, or to aske for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of it, and by an over-weening conceit of himſelfe, is ſo apprehenſive of any wrong done to him, that he judges it unreaſonable to paſſe it by: but humility will inable a man to all this: if then we would maintain peace among our ſelves, ſhun pride, labour for humility: for it is moſt true, that Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes, anſwerable to the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med paſſage of the wiſe man:<note place="margin">Aug. contra e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Parmen. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>humilitate pax cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita eſt, elatione dirupta eſt: humility conduces to peace, pride is a make-bate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Be not too vehement and impetuous in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king either wealth or honour:<note place="margin">Ier. 45.5.</note> 
               <hi>Seekeſt thou great things for thy ſelfe? ſeeke them not,</hi> ſayes God to <hi>Baruch</hi> by the Prophet: And indeed ſeeke them not, if we have a deſire to maintaine peace: for, as <hi>Arnobius</hi> ſayes well, <hi>non eſſet utique lis in ſeculo. ſi non unus alio vellet ditior fieri, vel in opibus vel in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arnob. in Pſal. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There would be no contention in the world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we did deſire to exceed each the other, either in wealth, or in honour.</hi> How frequently have we found covetouſueſſe and ambition to uſher in ſchiſme and diviſions? Thus; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies;<note place="margin">Tertul. contra <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinianos.</note> 
               <hi>Valentinus,</hi> hunting after and hoping for a Biſhopricke, and miſſing of it, another who had
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15290:31"/>ſuffered much for the name of Chriſt, being preferred before him, being hereat diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, became the head of a faction, who from him were called <hi>Valentinians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. tom. <hi>1.</hi> de paenit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Novatianus</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> being diſpleaſed that he miſſed of a Biſhopricke, which he hoped for, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the liſts againſt the Church, and made a fraction in it. And ſo have we found it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves. As we deſire then to be armed againſt diviſions, moderate our deſires of great things in this world.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Maintain righteouſneſſe in our dealings, let us be carefull <hi>Suum cuique tribuere,</hi> to give every man that, which belongs and is due to him: give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, according to the injunction of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 13 7.</note> 
               <hi>cuſtome, to whom cuſtome, honour, to whom honour, feare to whom feare is due.</hi> Give the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter his due, his double honour of reſpect and maintenance according to the lawes of God and the King, and ſo to every one elſe in his ſeverall kinde. The want of this care we have found to be the occaſion of fearefull breaches. In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it is, that the Poets have made peace the daughter of righteouſneſſe: ſo heathen <hi>Scipio</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de civit. Dei l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> could ſay, <hi>concordiam ſine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia eſſe non poſſe, that peace cannot be without righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi> And the ſame Father deſcanting upon thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſſe and peace have kiſſed each other,</hi> ſpeakes fully to this purpoſe, <hi>Fac juſtitiam &amp; habebis pacem; ſi non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maveris juſtitiam, pacem non habebis. Amant enim ſe duo iſta, juſtitia &amp; pax; duae amicae ſunt. Worke
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15290:31"/>righteouſneſſe, and thou ſhalt have peace,</hi> if thou love not righteouſneſſe, thou ſhalt not have peace: for theſe two, righteouſneſſe and peace, love each other, they are two friends. He addes, <hi>Tuforte unam vis, &amp; alteram non facis: nemo enim eſt, qui non vnlt pacem, ſed non omnes volunt operari juſtitiam. Interroga omnes, vultis pacem? reſpondet totum genus humanum, opto, cupio. Ama juſtitiam, quia duae amicae ſunt, mutuò ſe oſculantur. Haply thou wouldeſt have one, thou wouldeſt not doe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for there is no man which deſires not peace, but all have not a minde to worke righteouſneſſe. Aske all men, would yee have peace? all mankinde anſwers with one conſent: yes, with all our hearts. Then love righteouſneſſe, for theſe two are great friends, they kiſſe each other.</hi> He addes further, <hi>Si amicam pacis non amaveris, non te amabit ipſa pax, nec ad te ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet; inimicus es amicae meae, inquit pax, quid me quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris? Amica ſum juſtitiae, quemcunque invenero ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum amicae meae, non ad illum accedo: vis ergo veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ad pacem? fac juſtitiam: If thou loveſt not the friend of peace, neither will peace love thee, or come neare thee. Thou art an enemy to my friend, ſayes peace, why doſt thou ſeeke me? I am a friend of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; If I finde any man a foe to my friend, I will not have to doe with him. Wouldeſt thou therefore attaine peace? worke righteouſneſſe.</hi> And in the ſame place, deſcanting on thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Depart from evill, and doe good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 34.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeke peace and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it,</hi> he addes further, <hi>Declina à malo &amp; fac bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, id eſt, amajuſtitiam, tum quaere pacem, jam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim non diu quaeres illam, quia &amp; ipſa occurret tibi,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15290:32"/>ut oſculetur juſtitiam. Depart from evill, and doe good, that is, love and practiſe righteouſneſſe, then ſeeke peace, for now thou ſhalt not need long to ſeeke her, but ſhe will readily meet thee, that ſhee may kiſſe righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In doubtfull things, avoyd groundleſſe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions, and make charitable conſtructions, and be ready to accept of their juſt apologies, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whom we have entertained any hard or uncharitable thoughts. The want of care this way, hath beene the cauſe of much diviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene private men, and in the Church: men doe or ſay ſomething, which may admit of a various conſtruction: we for want of charity, interpret it the worſt way, and when they offer their defence, we refuſe to accept of it, or to beleeve it: hence iſſues breach of peace between man and man. So in the Church it is, in reſpect of her conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. She enjoynes this or that, which ſhe judges to make for order and decency in the ſervice of God; we are ready to calumniate it as idolatrous and ſuperſtitious; ſhe makes her proteſtation to the contrary, we refuſe to beleeve her, we ſtill continue to cry out, O Idolatry, O Popery! and hence proceed thoſe heavy breaches that are among us in the violent oppoſition of her Orders. As therefore we would end theſe diviſions, walke by this rule. It is a remarkable paſſage to this purpoſe recorded in the ſacred ſtory.<note place="margin">Ioſh 22.</note> The nine tribes and halfe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> have their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the one ſide of <hi>Iordan;</hi> the two tribes and halfe on the other ſide; theſe, having according
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15290:32"/>to their promiſe to <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſeene their brethren in poſſeſſion of their Countrey, and their enemies ſuppreſſed and vanquiſhed, are now at laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed by <hi>Ioſhua;</hi> and having now paſſed over <hi>Iordan,</hi> and being come into the Land of their poſſeſſion, they ſet up a great Altar by Iordan: this offends the reſt of the Tribes, and, as it might ſeeme to them moſt juſtly,<note place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>For no ſacrificing muſt be among them, but at ſome one place, which God ſhould chuſe,</hi> &amp; conſequently but one Altar is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, for what ſerves an Altar for, but for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices? For theſe therefore to erect a new Altar might ſeeme to be <hi>ſcandalum datum,</hi> a ſcandall gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: they conſtrue it as done with a minde to turn away from following the Lord, and thereupon they reſolve to make warre againſt them, but firſt they will ſend to them to heare what they could ſay for themſelves. <hi>Phineas</hi> and the ten Princes comming with him, charge them deeply with it, as done out of a rebellious intention. But when the two Tribes and halfe had made their juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that it was not done with any thought of forſaking the Lord, but onely to be a witneſſe, that though they might ſeeme to be parted each from other by <hi>Iordan</hi> running betweene them, yet they were all but one people, and had a joynt intereſt in one God. The other Tribes accepted of, and reſted in this their defence, and layed downe their purpoſe of warring againſt them: Oh that there were ſuch a charitable affection in men in theſe dayes; oh that whereas we have miſconſtrued uncharitably the conſtitutions of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15290:33"/>the Church our Mother, as ſuperſtitious, as uſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Popery, we could at laſt reſt in the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies publiſhed by authority, in which there is ſo cleare and ſerious a proteſtation to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: how would this tend to the conſervation of peace and unity?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Abſtaine from curious ſearch into unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table controverſies, and be not ſo much addicted and wedded to our private opinions about them, but that, being convinced of miſtakes therein, we may readily relinquiſh our errours, and ſubſcribe to the truth. This would much tend to peace, and make for it, and the contrary is oft an occaſion of no ſmall breaches. It is therefore good for us in this caſe to take up S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> reſolution, wherein he alludes to the words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>Knowledge puffeth up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>15.</hi> ad Hieron.</note> but love edifies. <hi>Minus aſſequatur,</hi> ſayes the Father, <hi>illa quae inflat, modò non offendatur illa, quae aedificat, Let that gaine leſſe, which puffes up, ſo that be not prejudiced that edifies:</hi> that is, let us content our ſelves to know leſſe, ſo we may be more charitable.</p>
            <p n="6">6 In indifferent things let us not be too ſtiffe, but yeelding: In thoſe things, in which we have full libertie of choice, be carefull, not to offend the weake,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.32.</note> but follow Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> advice, <hi>Give no offence, neither to the Iew, nor to the Greeke, nor to the Church of God.</hi> And take we up his reſolution. <hi>If meat make my brother to offend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>I'le eate no fleſh, while the world ſtands, leſt I ſhould make my brother to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend.</hi> Heare we what he ſayes,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>I know and am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by the Lord Ieſus, that there is nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15290:33"/>of it ſelfe, but to him that judges any thing to be uncleane, to him it is uncleane: but if thy brother be grieved with thy meat, now thou walkeſt not charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; Deſtroy not him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt dyed.</hi> But for other things in which being indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in themſelves (God having given no ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall order concerning them one way or other) we yet are limited by the command of authority, in theſe, out of our duty to ſuperiours, it is for us to ſubmit to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands. to be regulated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and by the ſetled cuſtome of the Church, if we would maintaine the peace of the Church. The things themſelves God hath neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded nor forbidden; but to obey authority in the things which God hath left free, this God hath commanded; and no leſſe hath he forbidden diſobedience herein by the fifth Commandment, which requires honour to ſuperiours, a principall branch whereof is obedience to them in ſuch commands as are not contrary to the will of God. It is this, which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes he learned from S. <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> he ſayes, that he moved this queſtion to him, <hi>Vtrum juxta morem Civitatis ſuae Sabbato je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junaret, an Eccleſiae Mediolanenſis more pranderet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>86.</hi> ad Caſulan. Preſbyter.</note> 
               <hi>Whether according to the cuſtome of his owne Citie he ſhould obſerve the Saturday faſt, or ſhould dine that day according to the cuſtome of the Church of Millaine,</hi> and that Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> returned him this anſwer. <hi>Quid poſſum hinc docere amplius, quam quod ipſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio? What can I teach you concerning this, more then that which I my ſelfe do?</hi> And whereas S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> thought that S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had enjoyned him not to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15290:34"/>obſerve the Saturday Faſt, becauſe he ſaw that he obſerved it not S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> explained himſelfe thus, <hi>Quando hic ſum, non jejuno Sabbato; quando Romae ſum, jejuno: When I am here,</hi> namely, at <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, I obſerve not the Saturday Faſt; when I am at Rome, I obſerve it.</hi> And ſo he added this generall rule, <hi>Ad quamcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Eccleſiam veneritis, ejus morem ſervate, ſi pati ſcandalum non vultis, nec facere. To whatſoever Church ye come, obſerve the cuſtome of it, if ye will not either take or give offence.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> addes of his own. <hi>Quia contingit, ut una Eccleſia habeat alios Sabbato jejunantes, alios pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, mos eorum mihi ſequendus videtur, quibus corum populorum congregatio regenda commiſſa eſt: Quare ſi meo conſilio acquieſcis, Epiſcopo tuo in hac re noli reſiſtere, &amp;, quod facit ipſe, ſine ullo ſcrupulo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare. Becauſe it ſo falls out, that in one and the ſame Church ſome may faſt on Saturdayes, and others dine, the cuſtome of thoſe ſeems to me to be followed, to whom the government of the Church is committed. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you reſt in my advice, reſiſt not thy Biſhop in this thing, and what he doth, follow thou without ſcruple.</hi> The obſervation of this rule, and care to walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, would, not a little, tend to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the peace and unity of the Church.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Shut out tale-bearers, if we would ſhun pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate breaches: there is a generation of men, that go up and down from one to another, carrying the devils pack like Pedlers, ſeeking to curry fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with all ſides: theſe are miſchievous perſons: <hi>A whiſperer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 16.28.</note> ſaith <hi>Solomon ſeparates chiefe friends.</hi> If therefore we deſire to maintaine peace, let us
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15290:34"/>walk by <hi>Solomons</hi> rule,<note place="margin">Prov. 25.23.</note> 
               <hi>As the North winde drives away raine, ſo doth the angry countenance the backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting tongue.</hi> And the iſſue we ſhall finde according to that other adage of his.<note place="margin">Prov. 26.20.</note> 
               <hi>Where no wood is, the fire goes out, and where no tale-bearer is, ſtrife ceaſes.</hi> And for the preventing of publick breaches, hearken to the counſell of Saint <hi>Paul. Mark them that cauſe diviſions, and avoid them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> There is a brood of ill-minded men, who care not what they ſay or write, whereby to worke in men an ill opinion of the Church, wherein they live, though never ſo apparantly falſe, and that they may the more eaſily inſinuate and winde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the mindes of well-meaning people, they will make a faire pretence of zeale for the good of the Church, as if all that they did were altogether for the preſervation of the truth of Doctrine, and the purity of Gods worſhip, when, God knows, it is, if not onely, at leaſt eſpecially, for their owne advantage, to raiſe themſelves a name by defaming of others, whoſe preferment they envy: ſuch as theſe the Apoſtle would have us to marke and avoid: and according to this is the advice of Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> that famous Biſhop of <hi>Carthage, Admoneo pariter &amp; conſulo,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pr. Epiſt <hi>40</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> plebem de quinque Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter. Schiſm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aticis factionis foeliciſſimi.</note> 
               <hi>ne pernicioſis vocibus temerè credatis, ne fallacibus verbis conſenſum facilè commodetis, ne pro luce tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, pro die noctem, venenum pro remedio, mortem pro vita ſumatis, nec aet as vos corum, nec authoritas fallat, &amp;c. I admoniſh and counſell you, that ye do not raſhly beleeve pernicious words, nor hand over head give aſſent to deceitfull ſpeeches, leſt ye take darkneſſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15290:35"/>for light, night for day, poyſon for remedie, and death for life: Let neither their age nor authoritie deceive you, &amp;c.</hi> Let this be our care, and we ſhall be well ſhielded againſt Schiſme and diviſion, and enabled to maintaine unity, and to live in peace; and ſo the God of love and peace ſhall be with us. To which God, Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, be rendred of us, and the whole Church, all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, praiſe, and power, might and majeſtie from this time forth and for evermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge <hi>3.</hi> line <hi>24.</hi> for Apoſtles, reade Apoſtle, p, <hi>6,</hi> l, <hi>3,</hi> for ſpirits, r, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. p, <hi>20,</hi> l, <hi>9,</hi> for diſſentio, r, diſſenſio, p, <hi>28,</hi> l, <hi>4,</hi> for ſlaughter, r, laughter, p, <hi>37,</hi> l, <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> for iniunction. r, iniunction, p, <hi>49,</hi> l, <hi>7,</hi> for pretend, r, did pretend, p, <hi>51,</hi> l, <hi>3,</hi> for defraudeiur, r, defraudetur, l, <hi>19,</hi> for Diaboli ſed pax, Dei, r, Diaboli, ſed pax Dei, p, <hi>52.</hi> l, <hi>23,</hi> for Saint <hi>Bernard; Hic et,</hi> r, Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, hic et,</hi> p, <hi>53,</hi> l, <hi>30,</hi> for, Thus; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> teſtifies; <hi>Valentinus</hi> hunting, r, Thus, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Valentinus</hi> hunting, &amp;c. p, <hi>57.</hi> l. <hi>27,</hi> for, God. The other, &amp;c. r. God; the other.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
